Participant: So you mentioned that you use some filters to try to detect errors in geographical space somewhat
but you don't use somewhat the n random space so you could also look for some plausibility of some of the new samples
with a kind of ecological test looking at the habitat niche
in Switzerland at least with the floristic database
which is then providing the data to GBIF, they are at the moment implementing a procedure
to use this as a plausibility test in addition to the geographic test
Leen Vandepitte : okay
what I talked about the quality control procedures those are now in the OBIS database.
They're not yet available through the portal so
there's no way yet of taking into account the results of those queries on the portal, they're working on that.
For the for the outliers,
they're using, it escapes me, they're using specific existing databases on salinity
and depth and some other things.
They're looking at that, in combination with other things to decide:  decide according to
the outlier analysis if it is an outlier or not.
At the end of the presentation, I gave two references to publications.
One of them has a complete description of the quality control procedures
that we have implemented and all the information will be there.
Participant: that's typically an example where I think we could improve a lot of procedures with some
of these filters using the environment and look at find a sample for a species in a very unlikely environment
Leen Vandepitte: Yeah
Participant: you can also just warn the person say can you check
Leen Vandepitte:  Yes.