Participant : Donald, you have staring the meeting with BHL, Catalogue of life, can you said a world on that ?
Donald Auburn : A couple of things there : first and foremost I think our one of our biggest needs
is to finish the long long long task of compiling first a global
effectively complete, it will never be
fully complete, catalog of the names that loan organisms.
And secondly to work in a way that is achievable and credible to
construct and maintain a complete classification of life on Earth at the species level a working one, there will
be disagreements.
Catalog of life and activities such as Iply and zoobank and index fundgorom have been working
on parts of this and we've had umbrella activities where we've talked about the global names architecture etc.
I am in closed discussion with Catalogue of Life
about, as you're aware, about how we merge our activities better we treated this is something where
we're going to build all of these things separately and and hopefully all will come out of it with benefit.
GBIF shouldn't be doing anything to stitch
together names and classifications
that is separate from what the catalog of
life is doing or IOL is doing, we need to
combine those activities and we need to do so in a way that ensures that those who have put decades of effort into building their own databases
feel comfortable and feel that they get the credit they need
but we're nevertheless those datasets can be things that the global community can maintain the take forward
so I try to work through a workshop, organizing a workshop in the next few months with catalog of life and with others
looking at the sociology of how we do that,
and I think sociology is the
real issue technically it's easy and
then I think GBIF can provide a lot of
these supports for Catalog of Life to accelerate what we're doing.
More broadly, we have had discussions with BHL, Encyclopedia of life, Catalog of life, The bar code of life database and others
about how we start making real linkages
between out our data.
And again, part of the trouble is that we're all trying to duplicate bits of each other's activity
and I wanted to move towards an ecosystem where we have a shared understanding
of the graph of connections between specimens and collections
and tax on concepts and tax on names and publications and sequences and traits
at the very highest level and that instead of duplicating bits of that
we actually have interconnected infrastructure's so that there is one place
for finding all of the names of organisms so that we work together to populate BHL to the fullest extent possible.
So that GBIF can provide a service that locates the type specimen it's been digitized
and connect it up with the intellectual record and with the publication.
That's what we've got to go.
We're still with
infrastructure's that are offering value
but aren't part of the globally connected knowledge space I would like to see.
Anyone who can throw their weight into finding ways to make this happen and it's all about
solving project timelines and the sociology of how we give credit,
and how we recognize the expertise of contributors.
It's a complicated issue because about people
but if we get it right then I think we can provide a much better service
to the research community to text on the miss and others. Not in short time.