Leen Vandepitte : My name is Leen Vandepitte,  I'm from the Flanders Marine Institute in Oostende, Belgium
and I'm the data manager for the European node of OBIS which is the Ocean Biogeographic Information System
and link to that I'm also involved in the world register of marine species.
Okay, what i will do is ; Anne-sophie has asked me me to talk about EurOBIS
and how is links to GBIF, so that's what I'll do.
I'll sketch a little bit what EurOBIS is,
the history about EurOBIS,
how is it linked to other initiatives for example OBIS,
and then how OBIS and GBIF fit together.
About 15 to 20 years ago if we would look in Belgium to a biological data, then we would know that it's very scattered
Everyone has a little data set somewhere but there's no way everything gets together
and biological data were also collected with very confined boundaries
and you're sense that if you would have or if you would do research on a project or PhD
you have your time frame of three to five years so your data is limited in time
it would also be limited in space because mostly you stick to one region for your PhD or your sampling
and you would also have
financial limitations because you have to take into account the budget that you have to do your sampling.
What happens is this isn't only the case in Belgium but it's all over Europe and even all over the world
and the similar thing that happens everywhere is that data get collected data get analized people publish on their data
and then they classify their data somewhere which is mostly on a CD
and a closet somewhere and after a while you just forget about the fact that you have them
and on top of that everybody is working on its own specific dematic group
people are working on male bentos you have people working on fish on macro bentos,
so it's very very diverse.
So if you look at all that then you kinda cannot help but wondering
how can we see the large-scale global patterns and all this if the data is so scattered everywhere ?
And the answer to that basically lies in bringing your data together.
GBIF does that but with in Belgium we have EurObus European Obus node,  which brought European marine data together.
And this all started with in the malabif project with which was a project on biodiversity and ecosystem functioning
specifically for the marine environment.
And after that EuroBIS was continued in several other projects
and, I'm not sure how many people here are familiar with marine research or the marine landscape,
but two very important projects here are imminent biology which
is funded by the European government and also Lifewatch which has been mentioned earlier today.
So if we look at EurOBIS, the original focus there was to have your taxons  distribution information in space and time.
So basically what is where at what time that's what we were looking at.
It started in 2004 so it's more than 10 years already that we're working on it
and in that time it has evolved in a sense that we're now
recently extended the database to also be able to deal with
measurement or facts which is basically biomass information.
Fish lengths for example, stomach analysis data of birds or fish, and so on.
And also a link with abiotic information because mostly when you collect biological sample
you also measure sediments,  the composition of the sediment temperature salinity and so on.
So all that can now be stored all together within the database.
Now the aims of EurOBIS were pretty simple,
it'll be aimed to be a one access point for all that data.
Easy access and free access, open access.
No passwords, no limitations on getting access to the data.
And the second aim, of course, is if you bring together all that scattered information is to be able to
help scientists to increase the understanding of the distribution and biodiversity, of the European marine life.
Next to that it also helps and identifying gaps in our knowledge
if we would have specific region that is uncovered for data then we know we have a gap and we should look into that.
And lastly, and that's very important for us, is
we try to give an indication of the fitness for use of the data of an indication on the quality
and the completeness of the data, and I'll get back to that in a minute.
First the database itself : it's an SQL database basically,
which is completely compatible with Darwin Core which is used by GBIF and IPT also.
It has metadata information we also have a system where we can assign DOIs on a data set level.
So DOI basically gives you an easy way of citing a data set when it is used and you can also keep track of the citations.
It has a current information and measurement or facts information.
The content,  I just looked at it earlier this week,
we almost have 700 data sets from a little bit more than 150 Institutes within Europe
There's twenty point seven million distribution records in there
and 5.5 million measurement or facts values
which are mostly biomass and abundance information.
And if you look at the species names in there, there's more than 63,000 species names that have been documented so far.
Forty-one percent of them are accepted species names,
but I'll get back to that later on because
lots of times, we get older data sets that use names that are now seen as a synonym of the accepted name's,
so that's why we have a large number of species names.
Just to give you an ID on the growth :  so we have the distribution records and the number of data sets.
It all started in early 2000s and it keeps on growing basically.
Now, EurOBIS as a database is really nice for us the European level we've been able to do a lot of work with European projects and so on.
But of course it's only a database and its value can become a lot bigger if it can be linked to one or two similar initiatives
so it's part of a bigger picture and this is really important.
So EurOBIS itself gets its data from several providers,
I'm listing a few of them there but the most important one right now are
the small scale and the short term data sets that people collect in the framework of PhD small research projects
And secondly the national monitoring data : each country has normally a monitoring program and what we've tried to do over the last year's
is to get access to those marine monitoring data to make them available.
We're takin data in several ways we're not picky on how people provide their data to us.
The easiest system for us is IPT.
Some data systems like Isis have their own web services so we can rides those.
We collaborate with SeaDataNet which is also a marine project.
We just basically also accept text files, Excel files, Access files, anything that contains information on a distribution of species.
we are willing to deal with that and format it so it fits into the database.
What we do : the data collection happens continuously but once a month we do an upload into the database and then data become available.
Data available within EurOBIS can be consulted through several ways the one on the left is
the EurOBIS data portal so that basically gives you an overview of data sets that we have and you can query it based on a species name for example.
The second one is the amount net biology portal is more sophisticated
because you can combine specific species traits with species names or species groups.
And then the third one is LifeWatch.
Which is not really a portal where you go to but delivers web services.
So there's ways of combining several web services to to get information for you.
So I really invite you to have a look at those portals and see what is available, see what is accessible,
it would take me too much time to go through them.
So EurOBIS, part of the bigger picture : it gets his information bottom up.
but it also provides its information to OBIS which is the international level, basically.
And OBIS, as you can see on the map, covers worldwide all the marine and seas and oceans
And OBIS itself doesn't only get its data from EurOBIS but gets it from a whole network of notes, all these nodes.
Those can either be regional like the
Does that work ? Okay.
So it can be reached now basically, for example USA, the African ones ;  it can be thematic;
OBIS map for example focuses on distribution information from marine mammals and sea turtles so you can find information there
And there's also smaller regions in this case for example MedOBIS and Black Sea OBIS.
So in total, there's 29 nodes that supply information to OBIS that help it grow
Each of those nodes is, again, depending on the whole network of local providers
so just the same as EurOBIS like, we gather data from european institutes and researchers ; the same goes for all the other nodes
That way OBIS being the agregator of all the information,  it can build a global alliance and set up a collaboration with scientific communities.
This really helps in getting free and open access by geographic data.
OBIS itself also has a data portal,
that's the link they just recently launched a renewed portal so it's still on beta
but again, we kindly invite everyone to have a look and even if you have any feedback or comments on the on the website itself,
you're more than welcome to to let us know.
What you can do, on the OBIS portal, again there are several options
to query the data and to get to statistics so you can group or you can look for data sets per country or Institute
per marine, world heritage site for example and based on what you ask for, you get
different results if you look for example at the data sets you get an overview of where is it coming, from how can you cite it,
what's the background on the data set what kind of data is in there  and so on.
Nice to know or good to know is that OBIS and EurOBIS are basically in the same building at Oostende.
It's two different Institute's that host OBIS and EurOBIS but we're in the same building ;
so being next door to each other really gives us opportunities to work closely together
One of those opportunities that we took is to start
developing quality control tools to be able to assess both the quality and the fitness of the data that we have in the data systems.
I'll just explain a little bit more about that.
So the aim of these quality control procedures is of course to help providers and data managers.
Because we check the quality, we check the completeness, we try to detect possible errors.
And on all those levels we give feedback to our original providers, so they are able to
if it would be a mistake to correct the data and to resend it to us.
What we do is we basically assign a quality flag to each available records.
But important here is to realize that we're not saying a record is good or bad,
we're just giving an indication of the fitness for purpose and the fitness for use.
By assigning those flags, we are helping people to filter out specific records with a certain quality standards.
I'll just give an example : one record could be "abra alba" which is  a tiny shell I have a picture there
and you know the latitude and longitude and you know what year and has been collected in.
What can you do with that record ?
It's a record that is perfectly suitable for a general distribution analysis because it's a species occurrence.
It's also suitable for a temporal analysis if you'd only look at the year,
because you know which year it was sample then but
it's not suitable for seasonal analysis because you're missing the day and the month.
It's not because you're missing the day and the month that you cannot do anything with it,
that's what we try to do, by assigning those quality flags,
it's to still give you an indication of what it can and cannot be used for.
It will also not be suitable for abundance analysis because you only know it is present you don't know how many they found in what region.
Okay.
How are we doing this ?
These quality control procedures in two ways :
we have an automated process which is running on the OBIS database
which assigns those quality flags to each individual record and which helps us to give feedback to all our providers.
Just to give you some background : it involves 28 different checks
subdivided in five big degrees being : taxonomy, geography, completeness of the records, the format of the data and information on outliers.
The second thing that we do is we offer a number of those quality checks as online web services,
which means that you as a researcher, can take your data set to the web services,
run it through it and get the results and then if there would be inconsistencies or errors, you can immediately correct your own data.
For LifeWatch that would be the URL where you can go to,
so it's on www.lifewatch.be and there's a section on data services (www.lifewatch.be/data-services)
and there's two that might be very relevant for some of you :
as the first one, as a very basic one, is show on map,
you just upload your lat(itude) and long(itude) and you put them on a map to
immediately visually check if all the coordinates or all the sampling locations are where you expect them to be.
The second one is a taxon match which means that you map your taxon names with existing standard registers.
For example : because we're in marine institutes, we have worms in there,
so you check your name against the world which there are marine species
but we're also offering non-marine registers ;  for example catalog of life is in there.
PESI is in there, which is a pan-european infrastructure that has marine and murmuring names.
There's plenty more still coming.
Just to give you an idea on the importance of the quality control procedures, a very basic one one is a taxonomic quality control,
so what you see on the left, is the number of species names and the number of rare species
that were counted when several data sets were combined into one.
Left as before it, so it's before quality control so just looking for example, for the Mediterranean, we had eleven hundred and twenty species names there
Now after a quality control so really checking is each name spelled correctly is the synonym already accepted name.
We reduce the number of species to a little bit over eight hundred.
So this really shows that your quality control on your taxonomic or on your taxonomy is really important.
It's highly needed especially, not necessarily if you're working on your own data set but if you start combining things then it really becomes important,
because if you don't do a check on your taxonomy and you have a spelling mistake or a name no longer in use,
then you still see that as a specious and you get a higher biodiversity range in the area that you're looking at
compared to what it actually is.
What we do for the marine datasets is just much with WoRMS
and if we do that much for EurOBIS and OBIS,
we keep track of the unique identifier
within WoRMS for each issues names.
Because OBIS and WoRMS are linked,
that means that if you have a synonym and an accepted name in OBIS,
both pointing to the same species
through the link with WoRMS if you query on either of those names, you get the records for both names
because the system knows this is basically the same so it brings things together.
A second check like I mentioned : the geographic quality check,
also very simple things that we're looking at so your latitude longitude needs to be different from 0;0.
If you plot that even an OBIS still, as 0-0 a hotspot on biodiversity on the map,
it's right off the coast of West Africa so it's still marine but it's incorrect in most cases that's what we know.
We also make sure that the latitude and longitude are between the 90s and 180s
because we know when you transfer for example from text to excel, weird things can happen with dots and commas
so that's a check that we do and since we are dealing with marine data
of course we are looking at
whether the points are actually in the sea or in an ocean
we do take into account a 20-kilometre buffer because we know that
not everybody documents his coordinates as precise.
We also have coastal datasets so we want to avoid that we
tag the coastal ones as being possibly incorrect.
Just an example :
this is an actual data set that we received so sightings and strandings of marine turtles, the UK and Ireland
Just looking at the map makes you know that something is wrong.
it's basically a very simple error it's a switching of the
no it's actually here a missing minus sign because we're working in decimal degrees.
What also happens very often is the switching of latitude and longitude, the columns get switched.
So mapping or using a visualization of your coordinates can really help you to
very fastly identify errors like this and very easily correct them .
What we do specifically on OBIS,  and this might relate a little bit to the to the previous talk on outliers or records that get  thrown out of specific analysis,
so what we do on the level of OBIS is we look for geographic outliers.
Geographic outliers within a data set.
I'll just show you an example also.
This is an ICES data set that we received
and it looks a bit strange it could be correct but at first look you think
the dots in Africa are certainly going to be an error.
That is like that.
But the second thing that you see is that you have a lot of points in the north and you have a lot of points in the south,
it might be okay but you're not quite sure.
First back to the dots on on lands : those are picked up
first of all by the geographic check, where we just plot the species and look at the 20-kilometer boundary of the coastline
and they also show up in the outliner analysis,
you just know they're they're wrong you have to you have to go back to your provider and check this.
But for the second batch, the ones in in orange,
they are okay because they're in the sea.
They're not on land so we're not sure,
but if we do this outlier analysis then
those still come out as possibly being incorrect because it doesn't quite match with the philosophy that's behind the outlier analysis.
What we do in cases like this is we go back to our provider .
What we saw indeed is when we talked to the provider
the land dots were definitely an error so those are corrected
and the Antarctic locations were also incorrect something went wrong while they were documenting the latitude and longitude
while the ones in the north are correct and they just showed up in the outlier analysis
because it's a bit of a sampling bias that happened within that data set.
These out Larry analysis can really help you getting a good feel of the data that you have available
and can help you a little bit better in deciding whether you should keep
certain records or whether you should discard them if you're doing an analysis.
Just the last example on the outliers : so the previous one was really within a data set just looking at the sampling locations.
What we also do on the level of OBIS is looking at environmental outliers on species level
So OBIS has all those databases or all those data sets put together
and the system goes through its species by species
and it combines all the observations of all the different data sets for one particular species
and then it doesn't outlier analysis on that.
It takes several things into account :
it takes into account geography depth, salinity and temperature.
And again the same thing as on the previous map :
so on the left it's looking at geography and
on the right it's looking at depth.
You see differences in the outlier analysis for geography something might be okay while for depth it might show up as a possible outlier.
Those are the ones that you want to look at in more detail.
So again we have done that, we have consulted
with literature with experts and with available ecological information
and that did show that the dots in the north are okay
while the dots in the Mediterranean Sea was actually a misidentification of that specific species
So again, here, outlier analysis can help you in deciding whether you want to keep a record or discard it.
Now OBIS data is very widely used
so is the GBIF data which was mentioned earlier,
so there are several publications that cite OBIS
there are several ways that people use the portal to explore OBIS to see what is in there.
For example for France you can just go to the portal and
get an overview of all the marine datasets from France that are currently available within the system.
If we then click through to a specific data set you get an overview of all the metadata
and here, on the right you also get an indication of the data quality, very basic.
Are we talking species or not ? Is a time indication there ? And so on.
So again an invitation to go to the portal yourself and see what it can do.
Now OBIS and GBIF : how do they relate ?
Because this is basically where we want to get to.
Just a summary again : so we have OBIS which is fed data through its different nodes : regional and thematic.
Basically GBIF has a very similar approach,
of how it works : with the bi-level biodiversity information facilities : the GBIF and the nodes. It's the same way.
So what happens in 2014 : an agreement was signed between OBIS and GBIF.
The agreement, very briefly, says that OBIS and GBIF are complementary initiatives with common goals.
It makes sense to work together.
And what they try to do or what we will try to do is work towards a maximizing of quantity quality completeness fitness for use
of all those marine biodiversity datasets that are accessible through both initiatives
Now this is on the,  what I like to call the fuzzy above us, OBIS and GBIF level,
but how does this translate to actually the nodes and what we can really do to share data is like this :
where will I start.
Okay, what has happened last year, is on the level of OBIS and GBIF.
GBIF has given OBIS a list of all it's available datasets, per country,
with an indication of the number  of species that are marine.
GBIF has used WoRMS to match all the species and to filter out the marine ones
Now OBIShas an overview of datasets that are 100-percent marine or for example 75% marine.
Those are the ones that we would like to focus on if we don't already have them.
So what will happen in practice is that the OBIS nodes,
at that level OBIS's nodes will start contacting GBIF nodes to see if
marine data sets from GBIF's nodes can feed into the OBIS node's
Then from the different OBIS nodes,  it will fit to OBIS ; so OBIS aiming for a complete overview of all marine datasets worldwide.
The whole thing or that the whole setup is to really encourage collaboration between
the OBIS nodes and the GBIF nodes because again we have the same goal :
OBIS is focusing on the marine environment, GBIF is focusing on all environments
but there can really still be in exchange because I'm betting that GBIF France has different contacts
within the country then we have from
EurOBIS so we can learn from each other we can really move things forward.
And important there is we already all have a lot of work so if we can avoid duplication of effort I think that's very welcome,
so we really should see who does what and how we can divide work and go from there.
Final slides : where to go to from now ?
What I've done this week is very quickly have a look at EurOBIS and see which data sets from France are already available, marine ones.
There more than the ones that I've listed here but those were the ones that really caught my eye,
my eye so we already have data from Ifremer, from IRD, from the museum here, from Observatoire océanologique.
There's already a lot of things moving but I'm guessing that there's still a lot more that can be shared.
I should really look into that.
So again, the future steps is that
the OBIS nodes will look at that list of GBIF datasets with marine species
per country and then the responsible nodes will contact the responsible GBIF nodes
to see how we can work together.
And again stressing it's a two-way data exchange we really want to avoid a duplication of effort.
That having set, from an EurOBIS point of view, I'm really looking forward to
have a talk with GBIF France and see how we can start this collaboration.
It's a long process, it always is it's a continuous thing but it might be good to establish first contact here and
see where we can go from there.
So thank you very much and I don't know if they're time for questions.
*cheering*