Donald Auburn : It's a great pleasure to be here today
France has always being one of the Core-stone participants in GBIF
a significant contributor to every part of our work and i'm very excited
to see that this event today and so many here to celebrate 10 years of GBIF France.
This presentation will touch on a few subjects there are many more things that could be talked about and I believe
many of them will be discussed at various points later in the day.
So GBIF is an international intergovernmental partnership
to mobilize biodiversity information for the widest possible good
primarily for research but ultimately also through research
to support sustainable development and other key decisions around the environment.
GBIF has a growing number of national participants and as I mentioned
France has been one of these from the very beginning and a key contributor
in the work of trying to engage with other
countries particularly french-speaking countries in Africa and elsewhere.
After 15 years of GBIF existence as a an  international collaborative activity
we can see that a significant number of
data records have been mobilized but perhaps even more clearly we can see that together,
we have much more work still to do.
If we think about Western Europe, North America, parts of Latin America, South Africa and australasia,
the volumes of data and the number of species represented in these datasets
is already very significant and a major outcome for
many institutions, many agencies and
many public groups sharing their data to
help us to put together a more complete picture.
But across much of Eastern Europe and Asia, North Africa and the Middle East especially,
and for many parts of the oceans,
the gaps are still very significant.
Nevertheless what we have been seeing year-by-year is
that GBIF is an increasingly important tool for researchers in a wide range of fields.
Those who are studying particular species or particular taxonomic groups
as a source of information on specimens held in the world's collections
and other recorded data on the distribution of these species.
But also for many others who are trying to apply some genuine evidence of biodiversity patterns
as part of their decisions around agro-biodiversity, human health
conservation land planning and responses
to climate change.
I made what is certainly a very partial list of some of the many significant ways in which
France has been one of the core collaborators in this activity to this point.
France has been a stable and significant
contributor to GBIF,
financially and through the government structures ; a very large number of data points have been mobilized
by French institutions, support has been given to other countries in the hosting of their data
through physical infrastructure but also a massive amount of activity has been led by France
in supporting the development of capacity and skills,
not just in this country but around the world
France has been one of our most regular
contributors to activities for mentoring
the development of biodiversity information facilities in other parts of the world,
has led through the financing under the Sud Expert Plants program of
significant activity and has been reinforcing GBIF as an international activity
by providing much of the assistance for translation of key materials information resources training products into French.
And right now, within this room, Anne-Sophie and Philippe GrandColas are two of the the members of
our active members in our committee and governance structures
and others have been very active in task forces and contributing significant input the ideas that underpin GBIF.
As with all of our participants the result of this is that
work that's character it's been carried on here at the Museum and through your agencies and universities
and other collections and public groups around France has helped
to contribute to the wider picture for many many countries of the patterns of their biodiversity.
So I wanted to stand back from
just from some of the things we'll be talking about today,  just to say a few things about the
global picture
and what I think we're all trying to do together ;
some of the more recent developments in the tools and services and processes
that GFIF has been supporting and where I think we should be trying to go in the next five years.
So first of all, just to to summarize from my perspective what I think GBIF is,
I think GBIF has three overarching rolls
the first of these and the one that
underpins everything else
is to remove obstacles to collaboration and sharing and use of biodiversity data.
All around the world,
researchers, government, officers and others are seeking to access and maintain
information that relates to biodiversity and helps them with their work or their studies.
And yet it's very hard for them all to benefit from the knowledge, the expertise, the data that is being gathered in other places.
And more than anything else, and at all scales from institutions through countries to the global level,
our work is to try to ensure that this information flows freely
and that the barriers that stop individuals being able to access and understand
the limitations and the value of this
information are remove.
Capacity-enhancement, training and basic improvements to underlying tools and software are key to this.
Secondly and the reason for which I think most people are currently aware of GBIF,
is as an organized evidence base for their recorded occurrence of species in time and space.
This is an important role trying to
ensure that whatever can degree of information we have
that helps us to understand where species have occurred in the past, where they occur
now,
can be brought together whether that's from literature, from collections, from molecular work,
ultimately from remote sensing citizen science.
All of these are sources, all with their own bases, all with their own weaknesses
but we're together they can help us to understand these critical patterns.
And GBIF most visible output to date has been to bring these things together
and to create the data set of around 650 million specimens observations that we see today.
But thirdly and in my mind
still something of an incomplete task but right at the heart of GBIF was brought into existence
is to help Natural History collections to work together to provide the platform that
supports collection management
and taxonomic research for the 21st century and beyond.
My vision here is that we move further than
characterizing specimens as species locations and dates
and try to bring in the richer information that is
digitized and managed by many collections including imagery including links to sequences and tissue samples etc.
To do this in a way that facilitates a taxonomic researcher or someone else anywhere in the world
being able to find those materials and to be able to interact with them as far as possible
as they would if they were in the institution's concerned ; they're always going to be limits on this but
I believe that a global infrastructure for
biodiversity and collections data should be focusing on how we achieve this more effective.
And turning this around thinking about
the Intergovernmental landscape
GBIF has a critical role in underpinning
some of the work of the conventional biological diversity
ipbes and the Group on Earth
Observations (GEO)
as a series of stacked layers trying to support governmental
activity globally
and through that, the kind of outcome seen in the IE targets and the sustainable development goals.
GBIF is the global source for
bringing together
data from throughout its network that can underpin modeling, biodiversity patterns
and therefore providing genuine evidence to underpin biodiversity just assessments and biodiversity commitments.
So a few things
that have been relatively recent advances in our network :
some of these seen incredibly dull but are actually much more significant
It's the dullest of
the all : data licenses.
At the time when GBIF was started 15 years ago, we didn't have creative commons licenses,
we relied on very specialized data
agreements with individual data publishers,
we left it open for any institution to include whatever terms he believed were necessary,
for users of data and ultimately this had significant issues.
It meant that a researcher was technically obliged to read through vast quantities of metadata
to decide whether or not they were really authorized to use data for their purposes.
This does not scale the kind of levels of data we now have
and so we focused on trying to ensure
that every data record, every data set within the GBIF network
is associated with a data license that is as free and open as possible.
I'm pleased to say that after about a year of working with our data publishers we're now at the stage where
90% of the data sets have indeed been associated with the digital license
and more than 90% of those datasets
are associated now with licenses that require at most
the attribution of the data when we provide mechanisms to make that as simple as possible.
This is is dull but it's really a sign
of a big move
towards making these data part of a public data space where we can
discuss and improve and work on them together.
I think that this direction is one with that will really facilitate much more exploration and
manipulation of these data.
Connected with this, we've also been working hard to ensure that
we increase the visibility of the efforts of all of those who have contributed.
All datasets within GBIF are now associated with digital object identifier and
every time anybody download data from
GBIF,
they receive a digital object identifier for that download which connects back with all of the source data sets.
As a result of this, we now have the tools in place that if somebody publishes a research paper
based in part on data they have access to the GFIF network
they don't have to do anything more than cite that digital object identifier
and we can start making the
connections with all of the the datasets
which have contributed to that work which I hope will help to expose much more clearly
the value of our shared activity.
GBIF historically has only focused on
presence data, evidence that a species
has been recorded in a place and then the links to the additional properties of the specimen or the observation
concerned.
We are now able to incorporate
a richer subset of the data from many
ecological monitoring sampling activities
including some fences and
science where we get a better measure of
the methodology the co-occurrence of species and where possible the relative abundance of species in those samples.
This is still something for which
GBIF is at the beginning
and I do not expect that it's going to be easy for us to join all of these data together
but there is significant value for us in having integrated access to these kinds of properties
because if nothing else it helps us to calibrate the significance of all of the other data
in terms of abundance of species in time and space.
We've been fortunate to receive from the
European Union significant funding over a 4 years period
to promote content mobilization and capacity enhancement particularly in Africa, the Caribbean and the Pacific.
And we're just right now, in the first stage of
kicking off projects associated with this
with around 970 000€ being spent in the next two years on projects in African countries
many of which have been supported in critical ways by GBIF France throught their capacity enhancement activities.
We look forward to this as a way to reinforce linkages especially with the future Sud expert plant to program.
One last thing.
it's continuing and for which France has been involved
is international collaboration
around tools and software.
The one specific example illustrated here and I believe we'll come back to this in other ways later,
is the reuse of tools developed by the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA)
in multiple countries and the contributions of those countries
including France, Spain, Scotland in this particular case here and others
in modifying these tools and making them more generally applicable.
I believe that this represents a real strengthening of the GFIF network as a way that many countries
can collaborate to ensure that national level stakeholders
and in, I hope, in the future, regions such
as the Pacific and the Caribbean
can have tools that really enable their researchers to explore the data that relates to their biodiversity in an effective way.
Those are just a few of the things that I'm excited about as as recent changes and enhancements in our activity.
I just want to look very
briefly forward, GFIF operates in a five-year cycle
we're just coming towards the end of one
of these cycles and
from 2017 will be entering appeared with a new strategic plan, a new funding model
and really trying to take GBIF forward to
the next stage
and we've identified five strategic priorities for that period and I think these are ones where
we really need to support and promote and benefit from cooperation everywhere within the global network.
Just a couple of words on each of these first of all,
GBIF exists to ensure the free access to data everything we do
is about making sure that we're delivering the right kind of data to meet the needs of real users
we were engaged in lots of capacity enhancement actively engaged in lots of informatics activities
but those are not the justification for GBIF,
we're here to ensure that the data are delivered in the right form.
So a growing part of our activities to communicate as clearly as we can with researchers
in different areas and domains and thematic focus points
to understand exactly what they are looking for in biodiversity data
to understand whether there are additional properties we need to be trying to mobilize,
how the metadata can be improved, which are the most critical gaps in data mobilization.
That should be targeted if we are to
support their needs.
Through this also to understand the kind of data products, data services that are most important to those researchers.
First and foremost : one of our priorities,
and some in this room have been involved in some of our task force's looking at this for different areas,
is to deliver relevant data.
But under pending that, we need to be thinking about the ways in which our data need further attention.
One of the most critical of these is around data quality.
We have always taken the position that data quality is not an absolutely fitness for use for different users will vary widely
a specimen which represents the type for a species may not have a precise locality it may not have a precise date
but is still absolutely essential for many key purposes.
On the other hand, for other users, we need to be making sure that we have the finest possible precision
for time and space that we understand as clearly as possible the basis for the identification
of the specimen and part of what we have to be doing together is to characterize the individual data records
and the global data set so
that we understand and communicate
exactly what it is : that is an offer and that we can work together to find ways to  improve it over time.
GBIF needs to address data gaps the most visible of these
are obviously the special ones because  we like to put points on maps
and then they will become clear and even the inconsistencies and
the underlying sources of data start to become really obvious.
Nevertheless we do have to put more
effort on
recognizing the areas where we most need to bring more data online.
Right now, I would say that
GFIF has three priority areas that we have to focus on
one is on those parts of the world where we have next no data at all, clearly
Russia, much of Eastern Europe, Asia,
North Africa and the Middle East
are very obvious and we're working and very enthusiastic about making better connections with data holders in regard to those regions
That's best way for us to think about the the geographic gaps.
For the taxonomic gaps i really believe that our focus should be
to be working even more closely with Natural History collections.
They will remain our best source for information on many species that are unlikely to be recorded in other ways.
We need to make sure that collections are well supported in the task of bringing all of those data online.
And thirdly, we need to be better focused on bringing in some of that sampling event date of the time series and indications of abundance
that help us to get more of a picture of a change
not only in space but also in time.
As we move into the next five-year period though I think we should be looked thinking even more at a fine scale about understanding
the places in which gaps in data discontinuities are particularly significant
for reducing the precision and effectiveness of analysis based on the data.
Two other priorities underpinning all of this,
we need to be doing a better job than we have to this point of linking up out by the best information infrastructure's.
We rely heavily on the work of Species 2000 and the Catalog of Life and
more regional activities in organizing the names and classifications of species
we want to do a better job of linking to the literature through the biodiversity heritage library and elsewhere
and to datasets on traits and sequences and other environmental attributes.
GBIF has to work closely with other research infrastructures and has to make sure that is well embedded  in geospatial data management.
This remains a big and significant challenge and one where things like the data licenses
and the digital object identifier a key to us taking a lead in these areas.
And lastly, I'm bring this right back full circle : we do need to continue to work to empower our global network
the curious diagrams are put up represent some of the models we've been trying to put in place to help
those who are supporting GBIF nodes and national biodiversity information facilities.
More of a roadmap set of guidance under which we can then provide better training tools and support
for focusing on how on the national level we deal with data mobilization,
supporting data users, improving data quality and strengthening the network that is at the heart of this
Most of our activity, one way or another, is targeted at supporting our global network
and doing that is not something that we can do purely as a centrally driven centrally funded thing.
It really depends on people in this room and in similar situations around the world or collaborating with a shared vision.
So I want to thank you again , thank you for this opportunity
I'm very pleased to be here.
I'm very pleased at having France such a key member in our network and I wish you a very successful day.
Thank you. *cheering*